Sonnet 130 by William Shakespeare
莎翁十四行诗第130首​
My mistress' eyes are nothing like the sun.
我爱人的眼光并非阳光灿烂
Coral is far more red than her lips' red.
珊瑚也远比她的双唇红艳
If snow be white, why then her breasts are dun.
她的胸脯也说不上雪白光鲜
If hairs be wires, black wires grow on her head.
满头乌丝 也无法比拟金线
I have seen roses damask'd, red and white.
我见过粉  红  雪白的玫瑰
But no such roses see I in her cheeks.
却没见一朵在她脸上绽放蓓蕾
And in some perfumes is there more delight than in the breath that from my mistress reeks.
有很多馥郁芬芳的香水  比我情人的呼吸更令人陶醉
I love to hear her speak,
我虽爱听她娇语呢喃
yet well I know that music hath a far more pleasing sound.
却知道  更好听的声音还是丝竹管弦
I grant I never saw a goddess go.
我也承认  我情人的举手投足之间
My mistress, when she walks, treads on the ground.
没一点儿让我想起天仙下凡
And yet, by heaven, I think my love as rare.
可是老天作证  我觉得我的爱人着实稀罕
As any she belied with false compare.
毫不逊色于那些矫饰的红颜